<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<class xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../../docs.xsd" id="build-first-ios-app">
	<title>Building your first Couchbase Lite iOS app</title>
	<description>Tutorial for building a Couchbase Lite app for an iOS device</description>

	<introduction>
		<paragraph>This tutorial shows you how to use Couchbase Lite in your iOS apps. The tutorial
			assumes you already know how to develop iOS apps and have Xcode 5 or later installed on
			your computer. </paragraph>
		<paragraph>If you need to learn about iOS programming, a good place to start is by reading
			Apple&#8217;s free tutorial, <external-ref
				href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/referencelibrary/GettingStarted/RoadMapiOS/index.html#//apple_ref/doc/uid/TP40011343"
				>Start Developing iOS Apps Today</external-ref>, which provides a hands-on introduction
			to iOS app development. To access the Apple tutorial, you need to register for a
				<external-ref href="https://developer.apple.com/register/index.action">free Apple
				developer account</external-ref>.</paragraph>
		
		<paragraph>The tutorial walks through creating a simple Hello World-style app called HelloCBL. By following the tutorial, you'll learn how to create a new Couchbase Lite iOS app, create a database, and interact with the database by using basic CRUD (create, read, update, and delete) operations.</paragraph>
		
		<paragraph>To make it easier to learn the basics and get started with Couchbase Lite, the program structure is highly simplified. HelloCBL does not have a UI and all code is placed in the application delegate class, <code>HCAppDelegate</code>. All output is sent to the Xcode console rather than the iPhone screen in the simulator. Rest assured, the other sample iOS apps that we provide do not take these shortcuts—they incorporate standard iOS software design and development practices.</paragraph>
				
		<paragraph>
			You can follow along with the tutorial and build the HelloCBL app yourself, or you can <external-ref href="https://github.com/couchbaselabs/couchbase-lite-tutorial-ios">download the HelloCBL code</external-ref> from GitHub.
		</paragraph>
	</introduction>
	<lessons>
		<xi:include href="1-create-project.xml"/>
		<xi:include href="2-create-manager-db.xml"/>
		<xi:include href="3-do-crud.xml"/>
		<xi:include href="4-add-sync-gateway.xml"/>
		<xi:include href="5-couchbase-lite-views.xml"/>
		<xi:include href="6-understanding-live-query.xml"/>
	</lessons>
</class>
