<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<set xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../../docs.xsd"
   id="rest-api">
    <title>Public REST API</title>
    <description>Public REST API for gateway functionality and synchronization between a Couchbase Lite application and a Couchbase Server database</description>
    <introduction>
       <paragraph>The Public REST API provides gateway functionality and synchronization between a Couchbase Lite application and a Couchbase Server database. This article introduces the Public REST API and includes an overview of the available resources.</paragraph>
       <section id="public-rest-api-resources">
          <title>Public REST API resources</title>
          <body>
             <note>In the URI paths shown below, any path component surrounded by curly braces, <code>{&#160;}</code>, is a placeholder for a name that can vary; for example, <code>{db}</code> refers to the name of the database.</note>
             <paragraph>Following are resources for the Sync (Public) REST API:</paragraph>
             <table>
                <header>
                   <row>
                      <entry>Category</entry>
                      <entry>URI path</entry>
                      <entry>Description</entry>
                   </row>
                </header>
                <body>
                   <row>
                      <entry>Servers</entry>
                      <entry><code>/</code></entry>
                      <entry>Performs operations on servers (Sync Gateway instances). Examples include getting information about a Sync Gateway instance and getting a list of all databases served by the instance.</entry>
                   </row>
                   <row>
                      <entry>Databases</entry>
                      <entry><code>/{db}</code></entry>
                      <entry>Performs operations on databases. Examples include configuring a new database and compacting a database. Some database operations operate on all or many documents in the database, for example, getting a changes feed for all documents.</entry>
                   </row>
                   <row>
                      <entry>Documents</entry>
                      <entry><code>/{db}/{doc}</code></entry>
                      <entry>Performs operations on specific documents. Examples include creating and deleting documents.</entry>
                   </row>
                   <row>
                      <entry>Attachments</entry>
                      <entry><code>/{db}/{doc}/{attachment}</code></entry>
                      <entry>Performs operations on document attachments. Examples include creating and deleting document attachments.</entry>
                   </row>
                   <row>
                      <entry>Local documents</entry>
                      <entry><code>/{db}/{doc}/{local-doc-id}</code></entry>
                      <entry>Performs operations on local documents. Examples include creating and deleting local documents.</entry>
                   </row>
                </body>
             </table>
          </body>
       </section>    
    </introduction>
</set>