<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<lesson xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../../docs.xsd" id="build-and-run">
    <title>Build and run</title>
    <description>Build the example app using the PhoneGap command line tools.</description>
    <introduction>
        <paragraph>Now that you have all the tools installed, you can build the Todo Lite app. If you have problems building the app, see the <ref href="troubleshooting-the-todo-lite-build">troubleshooting</ref> section.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>Get out a stopwatch, your 5 minutes starts now!</paragraph>
    </introduction>
    <tasks>
        
        <task id="launch-terminal">
            <title>Launch the terminal</title>
            <body>
                <paragraph>Open a terminal window and change to the directory that you want to store the Todo Lite project in.</paragraph>
            </body>
        </task>

        <task id="create-project">
            <title>Create a project</title>
            <body>
                <paragraph>Create a new PhoneGap project and change to it's directory:</paragraph>
                <code-block>
                    $ phonegap create todo-lite com.couchbase.TodoLite TodoLite
                    $ cd todo-lite
                </code-block>
                <paragraph>After you create a new PhoneGap project, the project directory contains a directory 
                    named <strong>www</strong>. The <strong>www</strong> directory contains a default application.</paragraph>
            </body>
        </task>

        <task id="add-couchbase">
            <title>Add the Couchbase Lite plug-in to your project</title>
            <body>
                <code-block>
                    $ phonegap local plugin add https://github.com/couchbaselabs/Couchbase-Lite-PhoneGap-Plugin.git
                </code-block>
            </body>
        </task>

        <task id="add-plugins">
            <title>Add the other plug-ins to your project</title>
            <body>
                <paragraph>The following additional plug-ins are used by the example app for various features. The app
                is partially functional even without them, so you can leave them out if you are troubleshooting.</paragraph>
                
                <code-block>
                    $ phonegap local plugin add https://git-wip-us.apache.org/repos/asf/cordova-plugin-camera.git
                    $ phonegap local plugin add https://github.com/apache/cordova-plugin-inappbrowser.git
                    $ phonegap local plugin add https://git-wip-us.apache.org/repos/asf/cordova-plugin-network-information.git
                </code-block>
                
                <paragraph>These plug-ins activate the camera, the InAppBrowser, and network information.</paragraph>
            </body>
        </task>
        
        <task id="clone-example-app">
            <title>Clone the example app source code</title>
            <body>
                <paragraph>Replace the default application in the <strong>www</strong> directory with the Todo Lite source code:</paragraph>
                
                <code-block>
                    $ rm -rf www
                    $ git clone https://github.com/couchbaselabs/TodoLite-PhoneGap.git www
                </code-block>
                <paragraph>Most of the application code is in <external-ref href="https://github.com/couchbaselabs/TodoLite-PhoneGap/blob/master/js/index.js">the index.js file.</external-ref></paragraph>
                <paragraph>When you develop your own app, replace the default application  in the <strong>www</strong> directory with your source code.</paragraph>
            </body>
        </task>

        <task id="launch-example-app-ios">
            <title>Launch the example app (iOS)</title>
            <body>
                <paragraph>Build and run the Todo Lite iOS app:</paragraph>
                
                <code-block>
                    $ phonegap run ios
                </code-block>
                
                <paragraph>The Todo Lite app opens in the iOS simulator. If the iOS simulator does not open automatically, make sure ios-sim is installed.</paragraph>
            </body>
        </task>
        
        <task id="launch-example-app-android">
            <title>Launch the example app (Android)</title>
            <body>
                <paragraph>Build and run the Todo Lite Android app:</paragraph>
                
                <code-block>
                    $ phonegap run android
                </code-block>
                
                <paragraph>The Todo Lite app opens in the Android simulator. If the Android simulator does not open and you are prompted to log on to the Adobe PhoneGap build service, your Android device emulator is not set up correctly. You do not need to sign up for the PhoneGap build service to run this example.</paragraph>
            </body>
        </task>
        
    </tasks>
</lesson>
