<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<class xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../../docs.xsd" id="build-first-xamarin-android-app">
	<title>Building your first Couchbase Lite Xamarin.Android app</title>
	<description>Tutorial for building a Couchbase Lite app for an Android device using Xamarin</description>

	<introduction>
		<paragraph>This tutorial shows you how to use Couchbase Lite in your Xamarin.Android apps and includes instructions for getting started with both Xamarin Studio and Visual Studio development environments. This tutorial assumes you are familiar with developing software for Android devices using Xamarin. If you are new to Xamarin.Android development, take a look at the free
			<external-ref href="http://developer.xamarin.com/guides/android/">developer guides</external-ref> in the Xamarin Developer Center before beginning to work with Couchbase Lite.</paragraph>
				
		<paragraph>The tutorial walks through creating a simple Couchbase Lite app. By following the tutorial, you will learn how to create a new Couchbase Lite Xamarin.Android app, create a database, and interact with the database by using basic CRUD (create, read, update, and delete) operations.</paragraph>
		
		<paragraph>To make it easier to learn the basics and get started with Couchbase Lite, the program structure is highly simplified. In the HelloWorld example app, there is no UI and all code is placed in the <code>MainActivity</code> class.</paragraph>
				
		<paragraph>
			You can follow along with the tutorial and build the CouchbaseEvent app yourself, or you can <external-ref href="https://github.com/couchbaselabs/couchbase-lite-tutorial-android">download the CouchbaseEvent code</external-ref> from GitHub.
		</paragraph>
	</introduction>
	<lessons>
		<xi:include href="1-get-started-xamarin-xs.xml"/>
		<xi:include href="2-get-started-xamarin-vs.xml"/>
		<xi:include href="3-starter-code-xamarin-android.xml" />
		<xi:include href="4-do-crud.xml"/>
		<xi:include href="5-add-sync-gateway.xml"/>
		<xi:include href="6-couchbase-lite-views.xml"/>
		<xi:include href="7-understanding-live-query.xml"/>
	</lessons>
</class>
