<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<class xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../docs.xsd" id="net-mobile">
   <title>.NET</title>
   <description>You will learn how to use the .NET framework to build applications for mobile phones running on the iOS operating systems. </description>
   <introduction>
      <paragraph>This section shows how to develop applications using Xamarin Studio and Couchbase Lite .NET library. </paragraph>
   </introduction>
   <lessons>
      <lesson id="before-you-begin">
         <title>Before you begin</title>
         <description>Install the necessary tools</description>
         <introduction>
            <paragraph>Before you can build an application with .NET, make sure you have the following tools on your computer. You might already have some of them installed.</paragraph>
         </introduction>
         <tasks>
            <task id="xamarin">
               <title>Install Xamarin Studio</title>
               <body>
                  <paragraph>If you don't already have it, download and set up <external-ref href="http://www.xamarin.com/">Xamarin Studio</external-ref>.</paragraph>
                  <ordered-list>
                     <list-item>Go to <external-ref href="http://www.xamarin.com">http://www.xamarin.com</external-ref> and download the Xamarin Studio.</list-item>
                     <list-item>Go to <external-ref href="http://developer.xamarin.com/guides/">Xamarin</external-ref> to learn how to install and use Xamarin Studio to develop mobile and desktop applications. You will need additional steps, such as a Xamarin.iOS license for building iOS apps through Xamarin, etc.</list-item>
                  </ordered-list>
               </body>
            </task>
            <task id="device-provision">
               <title>Provision your device</title>
               <body>
                  <paragraph>
                     Once you have downloaded and installed Xamarin studio and acquired the appropriate licenses, you will need to provision any devices, such as an iPhone or iPad, that you are developing for.
                     Learn more about provisioning devices for app development <external-ref href="http://developer.xamarin.com/guides/ios/getting_started/installation/device_provisioning/">here</external-ref>.
                  </paragraph>
               </body>
            </task>
            <task id="dl-cbl-net">
               <title>Download Couchbase Lite</title>
               <body>
                  <paragraph>
                     You can download Couchbase Lite .NET on <external-ref href="https://www.nuget.org/packages/Couchbase.Lite/">NuGet</external-ref><!--, or you can get it from the <external-ref href="https://components.xamarin.com/view/couchbase-lite-net">Xamarin component store</external-ref> -->.
                  </paragraph>
               </body>
            </task>
         </tasks>
      </lesson>
      
      <lesson id="building-todolite-net">
         <title>Building Todo Lite (Coming soon!)</title>
         <description>Get the example up and running locally</description>
         <introduction>
            <paragraph>Todo Lite is an example app for collaborative task list management. It illustrates many of the Couchbase Lite features, including document CRUD, binary attachments, view queries, authentication, and sync. Once you have it up and running you can read the source code to see examples of using Couchbase Lite in action.</paragraph>
            
            <paragraph>We are currently developing the .NET version of this example and it will be coming soon! Interim, you can check out some existing samples for .NET, such as GrocerySync and our Couchbase Connect conference app, <ref href="../../../../site/src/develop/samples.xml">here</ref>.</paragraph>
         </introduction>
      </lesson>
   </lessons>
</class>
