<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../../../docs.xsd"
         id="compatibility">
   <title>Compatibility</title>
   <description>TODO: Add description.</description>
   <introduction/>
   <topics>
      <topic id="is-couchbase-lite-compatible-with-apache-couchdb-">
         <title>Is Couchbase Lite compatible with Apache CouchDB?</title>
         <body>
            <paragraph>In the ways that matter, yes. The REST API is compatible, although you talk to the engine in-process rather than over a socket. Some of the more server-centric features of CouchDB, like user accounts, aren't supported.</paragraph>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="can-couchbase-lite-replicate-with-apache-couchdb-servers-">
         <title>Can Couchbase Lite replicate with Apache CouchDB servers?</title>
         <body>
            <paragraph>Yes, its replication protocol is entirely compatible. That's a very important goal. Apps using Couchbase Lite can sync with servers running Apache CouchDB and with Couchbase Server via Sync Gateway.</paragraph>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="can-couchbase-lite-replicate-with-couchbase-server-">
         <title>Can Couchbase Lite replicate with Couchbase Server?</title>
         <body>
            <paragraph>
               <external-ref href="https://github.com/couchbaselabs/sync-gateway">Sync Gateway</external-ref> acts as a server-side bridge between Couchbase Server and Couchbase Lite. After your data is synced to Couchbase Server, you can use MapReduce to build indexes across the full data set.</paragraph>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="does-couchbase-lite-have-conflict-handling-and-revision-trees-like-apache-couchdb-">
         <title>Does Couchbase Lite have conflict handling and revision trees like Apache CouchDB?</title>
         <body>
            <paragraph>Yes. Revision trees are implemented and preserved across replication.</paragraph>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="does-couchbase-lite-have-mapreduce-based-views-">
         <title>Does Couchbase Lite have MapReduce-based views?</title>
         <body>
            <paragraph>Yes, although for size reasons it doesn't include a JavaScript interpreter, so views are implemented in native code (for example, as blocks in Objective-C.) The same goes for filter and validation functions. It's possible to use JavaScript-based functions if you're willing to link in some extra code and libraries.</paragraph>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="can-you-access-couchbase-lite-over-http-">
         <title>Can you access Couchbase Lite over HTTP?</title>
         <body>
            <paragraph>There's an HTTP server extension called CouchbaseLiteListener. It's mostly there to enable Couchbase Lite-to-Couchbase Lite (peer-to-peer) replication,  make testing easier, and support PhoneGap-style HTML5 development.</paragraph>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="what-about-couchapps-">
         <title>What about CouchApps?</title>
         <body>
            <paragraph>
               <external-ref href="http://couchapp.org">CouchApps</external-ref> running in <external-ref href="http://phonegap.com/">PhoneGap</external-ref> is definitely an interesting mobile platform. We have a <external-ref href="https://github.com/couchbaselabs/Couchbase-Lite-PhoneGap-Plugin">Couchbase Lite Plug-in for PhoneGap</external-ref> that enables you to use Couchbase Lite with PhoneGap. Most CouchApps should be able to run with only minor modifications.</paragraph>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="why-sqlite-instead-of-a-b-tree-engine-like-berkeley-db-or-kyoto-cabinet-">
         <title>Why SQLite instead of a B-tree engine like Berkeley DB or Kyoto Cabinet?</title>
         <body>
            <paragraph>Largely because SQLite is already available as a shared library on every platform we're interested in. This keeps our code size down and simplifies the build process. It also comes with useful extensions like full-text indexing and R-trees (for geo-queries).</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Additionally, both Berkeley and Kyoto have GPL-like licenses that are less friendly to commercial developers (especially iOS developers) and incompatible with the Apache license of Couchbase Lite itself.</paragraph>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topics>
</article>
