<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../../docs.xsd"
         id="command-line-tool">
   <title>Configuration options</title>
   <description>A review of the Sync Gateway's configuration options and how you can administer them through the command-line.</description>
   <introduction>
      <paragraph>You can launch the <code>sync_gateway</code> with command-line options. However, in the long run, it's better to use JSON configuration files, which are the only way to serve multiple databases. You can also combine command-line options with configuration files. </paragraph>
      <paragraph>The format of the <code>sync_gateway</code> command is:</paragraph>
      <code-block>
sync_gateway [Options] [ConfigurationFile...] 
</code-block>
      <paragraph>
         <strong>Options</strong>
      </paragraph>
      <table>
         <header>
            <row>
               <entry>Option</entry>
               <entry>Default</entry>
               <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
         </header>
         <body>
            <row>
               <entry>
                  <code>-adminInterface</code>
               </entry>
               <entry>127.0.0.1:4985</entry>
               <entry>Port the Admin REST API  listens on</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
               <entry>
                  <code>-bucket</code>
               </entry>
               <entry>sync_gateway</entry>
               <entry>Name of the Couchbase bucket to use</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
               <entry>
                  <code>-dbname</code>
               </entry>
               <entry>bucket name</entry>
               <entry>Name of the database to serve via the Sync REST API</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
               <entry>
                  <code>-help</code>
               </entry>
               <entry>None</entry>
               <entry>Lists the available options and exits.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
               <entry>
                  <code>-interface</code>
               </entry>
               <entry>4984</entry>
               <entry>Port the Sync REST API listens on</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
               <entry>
                  <code>-log</code>
               </entry>
               <entry>None</entry>
               <entry>Comma-separated list of logging keywords to enable. The <code>HTTP</code> keyword is always enabled, which means HTTP requests and error responses are always logged.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
               <entry>
                  <code>-personaOrigin</code>
               </entry>
               <entry>None</entry>
               <entry>Base URL for Persona authentication. It should be the same URL that the client uses to reach the server.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
               <entry>
                  <code>-pool</code>
               </entry>
               <entry>default</entry>
               <entry>Couchbase Server pool name in which to find buckets</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
               <entry>
                  <code>-pretty</code>
               </entry>
               <entry>false</entry>
               <entry>Pretty-print JSON responses. This is useful for debugging, but reduces performance.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
               <entry>
                  <code>-url</code>
               </entry>
               <entry>walrus:</entry>
               <entry>URL of the database server. An HTTP URL implies Couchbase Server, a <code>walrus:</code> URL implies the built-in Walrus database.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
               <entry>
                  <code>-verbose</code>
               </entry>
               <entry>false</entry>
               <entry>Logs more information about requests.</entry>
            </row>
         </body>
      </table>
      <paragraph>The command-line tool uses the regular Go flag parser, so you can prefix options with one or two hyphen (-) characters and give option values either as a following argument or in the same argument after an equal sign (=). </paragraph>
      <paragraph>The following command  does not include any parameters and just uses the default values. It connects to the bucket named <code>sync_gateway</code> in the pool named <code>default</code> of the built-in Walrus database. It is served from port 4984, with the admin interface on port 4985.</paragraph>
      <code-block>
$ sync_gateway
</code-block>
      <paragraph>The following command creates an ephemeral, in-memory Walrus database, served as <code>db</code> and specifies pretty-printed JSON responses.</paragraph>
      <code-block>
$ sync_gateway -url=walrus: -bucket=db -pretty
</code-block>
      <paragraph>The following command uses a Walrus database that is persisted to a file named /tmp/walrus/db.walrus.</paragraph>
      <code-block>
$ sync_gateway -url=walrus:///tmp/walrus -bucket=db -pretty
</code-block>
   </introduction>
   <topics>
      <topic id="configuration-files">
         <title>Configuration Files</title>
         <body>
            <paragraph>Instead of entering the settings on the command-line, you can store them in a JSON file and then just provide the path to that file as a command-line argument. As a bonus, the file lets you run multiple databases.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>If you want to run multiple databases you can either add more entries to the <code>databases</code> property in the configuration file, or you can define each database in its own configuration file and list each of the configuration files on the command line.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Configuration files have one syntactic feature that's not standard JSON: any text between backticks (`) is treated as a string, even if it spans multiple lines or contains double-quotes. This makes it easy to embed JavaScript code , such as the sync function.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The following sample configuration file starts a server with the default settings:</paragraph>
            <code-block>
{
   "interface":":4984",
   "adminInterface":":4985",
   "log":["REST"],
   "databases":{
      "sync_gateway":{
         "server":"http://localhost:8091",
         "bucket":"sync_gateway",
         "sync":`function(doc) {channel(doc.channels);}`
      }
   }
}
</code-block>
            <paragraph>You can see an example of a more complex configuration file in the <external-ref href="https://github.com/couchbaselabs/CouchChat-iOS/blob/master/sync-gateway-config.json">CouchChat-iOS sample app</external-ref>.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The following command starts Sync Gateway with the parameters specified in a configuration file named config.json:</paragraph>
            <code-block>
$ sync_gateway config.json
</code-block>
            <paragraph>The following command starts Sync Gateway with the parameters specified in a configuration file named config.json and adds additional logging by including the -log option on the command line:</paragraph>
            <code-block>
$ sync_gateway -log=HTTP+,CRUD config.json
</code-block>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topics>
</article>
