<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="styles.css" title="Amy's CSS Stylesheet" alternate="no"?>
<guide xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../docs.xsd" id="wcbs">
    <title>Working with Couchbase Server</title>
    <description>Couchbase Mobile is designed to work with Couchbase Server.</description>
    <introduction>
        <paragraph>
            This guide provides information about working with Couchbase Server.
        </paragraph>
    </introduction>
    <articles>
        <article id="bucket-shadowing">
            <title>Bucket shadowing</title>
            <description>
                Bucket shadowing describes how to configure your Sync Gateway to work with a Couchbase Server app bucket.
            </description>
            <introduction>
                <note>Bucket shadowing is meant to enable sync for existing Couchbase Server apps. If you are creating a 
                    new app with both mobile and web clients, we recommend starting with the 
                    <external-ref href="http://developer.couchbase.com/mobile/develop/references/couchbase-lite/rest-api/index.html">Sync Gateway REST APIs</external-ref>, 
                    and connecting backend services using the <ref href="6-changes-worker-additional-processes.xml#pattern">Changes Worker Pattern</ref>.
                </note>

                <paragraph>Bucket shadowing allows the Sync Gateway to serve an existing
                    Couchbase Server bucket, making the contents of that bucket syncable with mobile
                    clients.</paragraph>
            </introduction>
            <topics>
                <topic id="How it works">
                    <title>How it works</title>
                    <body>
                        <paragraph>In bucket shadowing, the Sync Gateway manages its own bucket that contains the 
                            same documents as those contained in the Couchbase Server bucket it is "shadowing", 
                            but with the extra revision history metadata the Sync Gateway needs.</paragraph>
                        <section id="creation">
                            <title>Creation and updates</title>
                            <body>
                                <paragraph>
                                    Every time your app changes a document, the Sync Gateway detects that and copies the 
                                    change into its bucket as a new revision of the version-tracked document. And every time a 
                                    mobile client revises a gateway document, the current revision is saved to your app bucket.
                                </paragraph>        
                            </body>
                        </section>
                        <section id="deletion">
                            <title>Deletions</title>
                            <body>
                                <paragraph>Deletions in a Sync Gateway database are just special "tombstone" revisions. If you delete a document in the app bucket, a deletion revision gets added in the database. If a client deletes a document and syncs to the gateway, the deletion revision is replicated and causes the app-bucket document to be deleted.</paragraph>        
                            </body>
                        </section>
                        <section id="conflict">
                            <title>Conflict management</title>
                            <body>
                                <paragraph>
                                    So, what happens if the app updates a doc in the bucket at the same time that a mobile client pushes a change to it?  
                                    In the Sync Gateway's bucket you get a conflict, just as if two clients had changed the document. Both revisions exist, and one will be (arbitrarily) picked as the default. The default revision will then be copied back to the app bucket. When a client resolves the conflict by adding or deleting revisions, the resolved revision will be copied to the app bucket.
                                </paragraph>        
                            </body>
                        </section>
                    </body>
                </topic>
                <topic id="configuration">
                    <title>Configuration</title>
                    <body> 
                        <paragraph>We assume you already have a Couchbase Server with a app bucket whose
                            contents you want to make syncable.</paragraph> 
                        <paragraph>If you do not, you will need another Couchbase Server
                            bucket to act as the Sync Gateway bucket's shadow. This other bucket does not have to be on
                            the same server, although that's the most convenient way to do it. The
                            two servers just have to be mutually reachable.</paragraph>
                        <paragraph>Configure the Sync Gateway as per the existing documentation.
                            Then in your JSON configuration add a new property called <code>shadow</code> to
                            the configuration object for the database; its value must be an object with
                            properties <code>server</code> and <code>bucket</code>, representing the location of the app
                            bucket to shadow: </paragraph>
<code-block>
"databases": {
	"db": {
		"server": "http://localhost:8091",
        "bucket": "sync_gateway",
        "shadow": {
           "server": "http://localhost:8091",
           "bucket": "app_bucket"
        },
</code-block>
                        <paragraph>You can optionally add a <code>doc_id_regex</code> property,
                            whose value must be a regular expression: only document IDs / keys
                            matching this regex will be transferred (in either
                            direction).</paragraph>
                        <note>If you're running a cluster of multiple Sync Gateways serving
                            the same database, make sure that you add the <code>shadow</code> property to only
                            <strong>one</strong> gateway's configuration. Otherwise, you will have multiple tasks
                            simultaneously trying to copy the same documents to and from the app
                            bucket, which will result in collisions.</note>
                        <paragraph>You may also want to add the key <code>"Shadow"</code> to the top-level
                            configuration's <code>"log"</code> property, to get logging output from the
                            shadowing task.</paragraph>
                        <paragraph>When you start the Sync Gateway, it will run through the app bucket's
                            history (also known as its TAP feed), copying any new or changed documents into the
                            gateway database. Depending on how large the bucket is, this may take a
                            while. Unfortunately there's no way to bypass this on subsequent
                            launches of the Sync Gateway, due to limitations of the TAP feed
                            implementation.</paragraph>
                        <paragraph>If you shut down the Sync Gateway (or it crashes), and changes are
                            subsequently made to the app bucket, the gateway will find and apply
                            those changes when it next starts up. However, the reverse situation
                            doesn't work yet: if the app bucket becomes unavailable while the
                            gateway is running, changes made to the gateway's database won't get
                            propagated to the app bucket when it comes back.</paragraph>
                    </body>
                </topic>
                <topic id="deployment">
                    <title>Deployment Considerations</title>
                    <body>
                        <section id="storage">
                            <title>Storage usage</title>
                            <body>
                                <paragraph>This workflow does double the amount of storage needed for you application, and can potentially more because of the extra revision-history metadata. In the future, we may be able to avoid storing a copy of the document body in the gateway.</paragraph>
                            </body>
                        </section>
                        <section id="set-up">
                            <title>Set-up location</title>
                            <body>
                                <paragraph>The bucket used by the Sync Gateway does not have to be on the same Couchbase Server as the app bucket. In fact, there's probably a performance benefit to having them on separate servers, because the gateway's traffic won't be putting a load on the main server. (You could view the gateway as being a type of caching proxy for mobile clients.)</paragraph>
                            </body>
                        </section>
                        <section id="flushing">
                        	<title>Bucket flushing</title>
                        	<body>
                        		<paragraph>
                        			If you wish to delete all of your stored app data on Couchbase Server and you are using bucket shadowing, you will need to do the following steps to ensure a full removal:
                        		</paragraph>
                        		<ordered-list>
                        			<list-item>Stop the Sync Gateway(s) that are configured to shadow the app bucket.</list-item>
                        			<list-item>Delete and recreate the app bucket, or utilize Couchbase Server's flush option to flush the bucket. To learn more about flush, check out the Couchbase Server <external-ref href="http://docs.couchbase.com/couchbase-manual-2.5/cb-cli/#flushing-buckets">here</external-ref>.</list-item>
                        			<list-item>Delete the Sync Gateway-dedicated bucket that shadows the app bucket.</list-item>
                        			<list-item>Start again the Sync Gateway(s).</list-item>
                        		</ordered-list>
                        	</body>
                        </section>  
                    </body>
                </topic>
            </topics>
        </article>
    </articles>
</guide>
