<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../../../docs.xsd"
         id="features">
   <title>Features</title>
   <description>TODO: Add description.</description>
   <introduction>
      <paragraph>Couchbase Lite provides native APIs for iOS and Android that offer low-latency and offline access to data.</paragraph>
      <unordered-list>
         <list-item>
            <strong>JSON-based</strong>. Every document is a <external-ref href="http://json.org"/> object consisting of free-form key-value pairs. The values can contain arrays or even nested objects.This lets you structure your data in a way that's natural to your app, without having to deal with complex data normalization or joins.</list-item>
         <list-item>
            <strong>Schemaless</strong>. This means that you don't have to define a rigid data layout beforehand, and later go through complex migrations if you need to update it. Data layout is somewhat free-form, and records, called <emphasis>documents</emphasis>, can have different structures. A sophisticated MapReduce query engine enables you to perform efficient queries, even on large data sets, regardless of how you structure the data in your documents.</list-item>
         <list-item>Provides <strong>native, object-oriented APIs for iOS and Android devices</strong> that integrate with your app framework. These APIs can map database documents to your own native object model, let you work directly with JSON structures, or both. Additionally, apps built with web technologies can use the Couchbase Lite REST API (for example, JavaScript, C#, or Python applications).</list-item>
         <list-item>Supports <strong>replication</strong> with compatible database servers. This gives your app best-of-breed sync capabilities. Not only can the user's data stay in sync across multiple devices, but multiple users' data can be synced together.</list-item>
         <list-item>Supports <strong>peer-to-peer replication</strong>. By adding an extra HTTP listener component, your app can accept connections from other devices running Couchbase Lite and exchange data with them.

<unordered-list>
               <list-item>Supports <strong>low-latency</strong> and <strong>offline</strong> access to data. In contrast with the frequent network request and response cycle of a traditional networked app, you work primarily with local data. This means your app remains responsive whether it's on WiFi, a slow cell network, or offline. The user can even modify data while offline, and it'll be synced to the server as soon as possible.</list-item>
            </unordered-list>
         </list-item>
      </unordered-list>
   </introduction>
</article>
