<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../../../docs.xsd"
         id="why-use-couchbase-lite-">
   <title>Why Use Couchbase Lite?</title>
   <description>TODO: Add description.</description>
   <introduction>
      <paragraph>The world has gone mobile—both businesses and consumers have leapt on the bandwagon. By using Couchbase Lite, you can provide your customers with a seamless mobile experience.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Businesses are moving to mobile solutions to provide better customer experiences and operate their businesses more efficiently.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Today's consumers rely on mobile apps to organize their lives and keep up with family and friends. They have smartphones <emphasis>and</emphasis> tablets. They want to keep their data synched between multiple devices <emphasis>and</emphasis> multiple people. For example, all members of a family could use an app that helps them coordinate schedules and shopping lists.</paragraph>
   </introduction>
   <topics>
      <topic id="json-anywhere">
         <title>JSON Anywhere</title>
         <body>
            <paragraph>By using flexible JSON documents rather than a rigid schema, your database can evolve over time without impacting the user experience. Your users can count on having an amazing app experience with a fast and unbreakable local database.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Couchbase Lite provides an ultra-lightweight, reliable, secure JSON database built for all your online and offline mobile application needs.</paragraph>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="easy-sync">
         <title>Easy Sync</title>
         <body>
            <paragraph>Couchbase Lite provides a sync solution that already works. It's easy to set up, easy to manage, and easy to scale. Data syncing is crucial for mobile apps:</paragraph>
            <unordered-list>
               <list-item>
                  <paragraph>Customers want to work with their data on multiple devices—smartphones, tablets, and desktop computers.</paragraph>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <paragraph>Groups of users want to collaborate on shared data.</paragraph>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <paragraph>Businesses want to update data sets in one central place and have the updates delivered efficiently to clients..</paragraph>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <paragraph>Users want responsive apps that let them work offline.</paragraph>
               </list-item>
            </unordered-list>
            <paragraph>Syncing is very difficult to implement properly. It requires special metadata (like vector clocks or revision trees), has to handle network partition and data conflicts, and its algorithms have to work incrementally and be highly failure-tolerant. Some mobile developers have waded into ad hoc sync implementations and found themselves in over their heads, with delayed or canceled products. Couchbase Lite provides sync compatibility with a solution that already works, Couchbase Sync Gateway.</paragraph>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="use-cases">
         <title>Use Cases</title>
         <body>
            <paragraph>Couchbase Lite technology boosts customer satisfaction in industries such as medicine, retail, travel, transportation, and social media. Couchbase has been working with community users and customers on use cases like these:</paragraph>
            <unordered-list>
               <list-item>
                  <paragraph>Medical Records—medical data is a great fit for schemaless JSON storage. It's also critical that it be available wherever the health care provider goes, regardless of network conditions.</paragraph>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <paragraph>Customer Loyalty and Point of Sale—we see a lot of these apps already using our sync technology, and we've been working with some developers closely to ensure a smooth ride.</paragraph>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <paragraph>Airline—pilots and flight attendants benefit from having easy access to data about passengers and flight plans, with the ability to dynamically refresh the data when they are on the ground.</paragraph>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <paragraph>Fleet Management—tracking vehicle telemetry and routing it to the cloud when connections are available is a great fit for Couchbase Mobile.</paragraph>
               </list-item>
               <list-item>
                  <paragraph>Social Media—chat and game companies often take a portfolio approach. By offloading the details of pushing data across mobile networks, they can focus on rolling out compelling content that uses a common backbone.</paragraph>
               </list-item>
            </unordered-list>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topics>
</article>
