<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../../docs.xsd"
   id="notation-conventions">
    <title>Notation conventions for Sync Gateway REST API endpoints</title>
    <description>Notation conventions for representing static and variable path segments of endpoint URIs for the Sync Gateway REST APIs</description>
    <introduction>
       <paragraph>The Sync Gateway API References use specific notation conventions for representing static and variable path segments of REST endpoint URIs.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>Within the paths of the URIs presented in these guides:</paragraph>
                <unordered-list>
                   <list-item>
                      <paragraph>Path segments that start with an underscore character are static path segments of the URI that you use exactly as shown, for example: <code>_replicate</code>.</paragraph>
                   </list-item>
                   <list-item>
                      <paragraph>Path segments that do not start with an underscore character are variables that you replace with your own values. To emphasize that these path segments are variables, we enclose them in curly braces as a reminder, for example: <code>{db}</code>.</paragraph>
                      <note>Some places in the documentation, you also will see angle brackets used as the indication of a variable path segment, for example, <code>&lt;db&gt;</code>.</note>
                   </list-item>
                </unordered-list>
                <paragraph>For example, suppose you have a database named <code>cookbook</code>. In the database, the IDs for documents that contain recipes start with the string <code>recipe</code>. The following table gives examples of values that you might use for the URI path in requests that you send to the database:</paragraph>
                <table>
                   <header>
                      <row>
                         <entry>Path</entry>
                         <entry>Sample value</entry>
                      </row>
                   </header>
                   <body>
                      <row>
                         <entry>
                            <code>/{db}</code>
                         </entry>
                         <entry>
                            <code>/cookbook</code>
                         </entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                         <entry>
                            <code>/{db}/_changes</code>
                         </entry>
                         <entry>
                            <code>/cookbook/_changes</code>
                         </entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                         <entry>
                            <code>{db}/{doc}</code>
                         </entry>
                         <entry>
                            <code>/cookbook/recipe123</code>
                         </entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                         <entry>
                            <code>/_replicate</code>
                         </entry>
                         <entry>
                            <code>/_replicate</code>
                         </entry>
                      </row>
                   </body>
                </table>
    </introduction>
</article>