<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<lesson xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../docs.xsd" id="prepare">
    <title>Prepare your workstation</title>
    <description>Get the tools and libraries</description>
    <introduction>
        <paragraph>The PhoneGap development environment and our example application requires a few tools to be installed. 
            This lesson will get you ready to clone, build and run the app.
        </paragraph>
    </introduction>
    <tasks>
        
        <task id="install-git">
            <title>Install Git</title>
            <body>
                <paragraph><external-ref href="http://git-scm.com/">Git</external-ref> is the easiest way to download the example application code. We'll also use it to fetch the 
                    Couchbase Lite PhoneGap Plugin. It's possible to get through these steps without Git, if you prefer.</paragraph>
            </body>
        </task>

        <task id="install-phonegap">
            <title>Install the PhoneGap tools</title>
            <body>
                <paragraph>The PhoneGap tools are implemented in Node.js and installed via the Node Package Manager.</paragraph>
                <ordered-list>
                    <list-item>
                        <paragraph>Install the <external-ref
                            href="http://nodejs.org/">latest version of Node.js</external-ref> . It should be greater than version 0.10, 
                            you can see which version of node you are using by running <code>node -v</code>.</paragraph>
                    </list-item>

                    <list-item>
                        <paragraph>
                            Use npm to install the PhoneGap tools by running <code>npm install -g phonegap</code>. Note the 
                            <code>-g</code> flag means "install globally" so it should install such that <code>phonegap</code> 
                            command is in your shell PATH. One consequence of this is that on certain systems, you might be
                            required to prefix the install command with "sudo" before it can write to the global package store.
                        </paragraph>
                    </list-item>

                    <list-item>
                        <paragraph>Verify your PhoneGap installation is complete by running <code>phonegap -v</code> to print the version. 
                            At the time of this writing the version is <code>3.4.0-0.19.21</code>.</paragraph>
                    </list-item>
                    
                </ordered-list>
            </body>
        </task>
        
        
        <task id="install-ios">
            <title>Install the iOS platform tools.</title>
            <body>
                <paragraph>The iOS tools are used by PhoneGap to compile and run your applications.
                    <ref href="#install-android">(Or skip to the next section if you prefer Android.)</ref>
                    </paragraph>
                <ordered-list>
                    <list-item>
                        <paragraph>Install <external-ref
                            href="https://developer.apple.com/xcode/">Xcode</external-ref>. These docs are based on Xcode 5.</paragraph>
                    </list-item>
                    
                    <list-item>
                        <paragraph>Once Xcode is installed, several command-line tools need to be enabled for PhoneGap to run. 
                            From the Xcode menu, select Preferences, then the Downloads tab. From the Components panel, press the 
                            Install button next to the Command Line Tools listing.</paragraph>
                    </list-item>
                    
                    <list-item>
                        <paragraph>
                            To launch your app on the simulator from PhoneGap you'll need 
                            <external-ref href="https://github.com/phonegap/ios-sim">ios-sim</external-ref>. The easiest way to 
                            install it is via <external-ref href="http://brew.sh/">Homebrew</external-ref>.
                        </paragraph>
                    </list-item>
                </ordered-list>
                <paragraph>For additional information about setting up your iOS development environment, refer to the 
                    <external-ref href="http://docs.phonegap.com/en/3.0.0/guide_platforms_ios_index.md.html#iOS%20Platform%20Guide">PhoneGap iOS Platform Guide</external-ref>.
                </paragraph>
            </body>
        </task>
        
        <task id="install-android">
            <title>Install the Android platform tools.</title>
            <body>
                <paragraph>The Android tools are used by PhoneGap to compile and run your applications.</paragraph>
                <ordered-list>
                    
                    <list-item>
                        <paragraph>Install <external-ref
                            href="http://ant.apache.org">Apache Ant</external-ref>.</paragraph>
                    </list-item>
                    
                    <list-item>
                        <paragraph>Install <external-ref
                            href="http://developer.android.com/sdk/installing/studio.html">Android Studio</external-ref>.</paragraph>
                    </list-item>
                    
                    <list-item>
                        <paragraph>Install the Android SDK by using the Android SDK Manager. If you have a project open in Android Studio, 
                            you can run the SDK Manager by selecting <strong>Tools > Android > SDK Manager</strong>.</paragraph>
                    </list-item>
                    
                    <list-item>
                        <paragraph>Set up an Android emulator by using the Android AVD Manager. If you have a project open in Android Studio, 
                            you can run the AVD Manager by selecting <strong>Tools > Android > AVD Manager</strong>.</paragraph>
                    </list-item>
                    
                    <list-item>
                        <paragraph>
                            Add paths to the Android SDK tools and platform tools to your system's
                            PATH environment variable; for example, on Mac OS X add the following:
                        </paragraph>
                        <code-block>
                            /Applications/Android Studio.app/sdk/tools
                            /Applications/Android Studio.app/sdk/platform-tools 
                        </code-block>
                    </list-item>
                    
                </ordered-list>
                <paragraph>For additional information about setting up your Android development environment, refer to the 
                    <external-ref href="http://docs.phonegap.com/en/3.0.0/guide_platforms_android_index.md.html#Android%20Platform%20Guide">PhoneGap Android Platform Guide</external-ref>.
                </paragraph>
            </body>
        </task>
        
    </tasks>
</lesson>
