<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<lesson xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../docs.xsd" id="troubleshooting">
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    <description>Find out why it didn't do what you expected.</description>
    
    <introduction>
        <paragraph>If you cannot build the ToDo Lite app, review the troubleshooting tips in this section.</paragraph>
    </introduction>
    <tasks>
        
        <task id="troubleshooting-tools">
            <title>Verify tool installations</title>
            <body>
                <paragraph>If you can't build the ToDo Lite app, first make sure you have all the tools listed in <ref href="prepare.xml">Prepare your workstation</ref> installed and that you have the latest released version of each tool. </paragraph>
                <paragraph>To verify that the command-line tools are installed and check version numbers, you can run the following commands in a terminal window:</paragraph>
                <code-block>
                    $ git --version
                    $ brew -v
                    $ ios-sim --version
                    $ node -v
                    $ npm -v
                    $ phonegap -v
                </code-block>
            </body>
        </task>

        <task id="troubleshooting-sdks">
            <title>Troubleshooting SDKs</title>
            <body>
                <paragraph>To make sure PhoneGap and your IDEs are set up correctly, try building the default PhoneGap app for iOS and Android: </paragraph>
                <code-block>
                    $ phonegap create my-app
                    $ cd my-app
                    $ phonegap run ios
                    $ phonegap run android
                </code-block>
                <paragraph>For more information about setting up the SDKs on your computer, see:</paragraph>
                <unordered-list>
                    <list-item>
                        <paragraph>
                            <external-ref href="http://docs.phonegap.com/en/3.0.0/guide_platforms_ios_index.md.html#iOS%20Platform%20Guide">PhoneGap iOS Platform Guide</external-ref>
                        </paragraph>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                        <paragraph>
                            <external-ref href="http://docs.phonegap.com/en/3.0.0/guide_platforms_android_index.md.html#Android%20Platform%20Guide">PhoneGap Android Platform Guide</external-ref> 
                        </paragraph>
                    </list-item>
                </unordered-list>
            </body>
        </task>

        <task id="troubleshooting-other-problems">
            <title>Troubleshooting Other Problems</title>
            <body>
                <paragraph>The following table contains solutions for some other problems you might encounter when building the ToDo Lite app:</paragraph>
                <table>
                    <header>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Problem</entry>
                            <entry>Solution</entry>
                        </row>
                    </header>
                    <body>
                        <row>
                            <entry>You can't install a command-line tool.</entry>
                            <entry>Use the <code>sudo</code> command to install the tool. For example: <code>sudo npm install -g phonegap</code>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>When you add plug-ins to your project, you get the following error message: [error] project directory could not be found.</entry>
                            <entry>Make sure you are in the <strong>/todo-lite</strong> directory.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>When you build an iOS app, the iOS simulator doesn't start automatically.</entry>
                            <entry>Make sure ios-sim is installed.</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>When you build an Android app, it uses the remote environment and prompts you to log on to the PhoneGap build service.</entry>
                            <entry>Make sure your Android device emulator is set up. For more information about setting up an emulator, read the <external-ref href="http://docs.phonegap.com/en/3.0.0/guide_platforms_android_index.md.html#Android%20Platform%20Guide">Deploy to Emulator section in the <emphasis>PhoneGap Android Platform Guide</emphasis>
                            </external-ref>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>When attempting to run the app for Android, you encounter the following error: <emphasis>[error] An error occurred during creation of android sub-project</emphasis>.</entry>
                            <entry>Ensure that the Android SDK <strong>tools</strong> and <strong>platform-tools</strong> directories are added to your system's PATH environment variable.</entry>
                        </row>
                    </body>
                </table>
            </body>
        </task>
        
        <task id="using-apache-cordova">
            <title>Using Apache Cordova</title>
            <body>
                <paragraph>If you cannot access the Couchbase Lite Plug-in for PhoneGap in the GitHub repository, you can use the Cordova download as an alternative. You can build apps with the Couchbase Lite Plug-in for PhoneGap by using <external-ref href="http://cordova.apache.org">Cordova</external-ref> instead of PhoneGap. The Couchbase Lite Plug-in for PhoneGap is listed on the <external-ref href="http://plugins.cordova.io/#/com.couchbase.lite.phonegap">Cordova Plugin Registry</external-ref>. </paragraph>
                <paragraph>When using Cordova, you install the Couchbase Lite Plug-in for PhoneGap into your app by using the Cordova command-line tool.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>To install Cordova on your computer:</paragraph>
                <code-block>
                    $ npm install -g cordova
                </code-block>
                <paragraph>If you can't install Cordova with this command, try <code>sudo npm install -g cordova</code> instead.</paragraph>
                <paragraph>To use Cordova to add the Couchbase Lite Plug-in for PhoneGap to your app:</paragraph>
                <code-block>
                    $ cd your/project/directory
                    $ cordova local plugin add com.couchbase.lite.phonegap
                </code-block>
            </body>
        </task>
        
    </tasks>
</lesson>
