<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<lesson xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
        xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../../../docs.xsd" id="understanding-live-query">
    <title>Understanding a LiveQuery</title>
    <description></description>
    <introduction>
        <paragraph>
            To help us track the constant changes that could be occurring in mobile applications, Couchbase Lite has an implementation of the Observer pattern known as a <strong>LiveQuery</strong>. We will use LiveQuery to go deeper into the possibilities of how listening for changes on the server can help us keep the data presented in the mobile client up to date.
        </paragraph>
    </introduction>

    <tasks>
        <task id="introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <body>
                <paragraph>
                    LiveQuery is a type of observer on the Query object and is encapsulated by the class <code>Couchbase.Lite.LiveQuery</code>.

                    <paragraph>A LiveQuery watches for changes in a view index or the database and automatically runs the underlying query. If any changes occur in the query, observers are notified of results.</paragraph>

                    <paragraph>
                    We get a LiveQuery from the Query factory method <code>ToLiveQuery</code>. Since the LiveQuery comes from the Query itself, which contains data from the View, the LiveQuery is already set up to observe the Query data. We observe that data via the <code>Changed</code> event.</paragraph>

                    <paragraph>To be notified of any remote changes to the data underlying the Query, we need to:</paragraph>

                    <ordered-list>
                        <list-item>
                            Register for the LiveQuery <code>Changed</code> event.
                        </list-item>
                        <list-item>
                            Start the LiveQuery so it is listening for changes to the data bound by the Query.
                        </list-item>
                    </ordered-list>
                </paragraph>

                <paragraph>The following code shows how to create and to set up a a LiveQuery:</paragraph>

                <code-block language="C#"><![CDATA[
                    var liveQuery = eventsByDateView.CreateQuery ().ToLiveQuery ();
                    liveQuery.Changed += (object sender, QueryChangeEventArgs e) => {
                        Debug.WriteLine("Data changed in the query", TAG);
                    };
                    liveQuery.Start ();
                ]]>
                </code-block>

                <paragraph>
                  <ordered-list>
                    <list-item>
                        First we obtain a <code>LiveQuery</code> via the <code>CreateQuery</code> method and assign it to a variable, <code>liveQuery</code>.
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                        Then we add an event handler for the Changed event on the LiveQuery in order to respond to data changes in our Query.
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                        Within the handler we can respond to any data changes as desired. Here we simply write to the log.
                    </list-item>
                </ordered-list>
 
                </paragraph>
            </body>
        </task>

        <task id="the-change-event">
            <title>The Changed Event</title>
            <body>

                <paragraph>
                The LiveQuery is listening for changes on document versions. For example, say that 'DocumentA' is part of the Query.  When the revision of 'DocumentA' is saved after an update, there will be a new version of 'DocumentA' automatically generated. With the new document version being available for Reads, this will cause the Changed event to be raised.  This means that:        
                </paragraph>

                  <ordered-list>
                    <list-item>
                        Every version of a document causes a new Changed event to be raised such that if 'DocumentA' had one data element updated, an “address” property for example, then the Changed event is fired.
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                        Also, if 'DocumentA' has multiple data property values changed, such as “address”, “date”, and “description” fields say, then only one Changed event would still be fired. The reason is that LiveQuery only listens at the document version level, not at the data attribute level within the document.
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                        Furthermore, we receive the Changed event, but no details about what changed within the document.
                        Therefore, the LiveQuery notifies the Changed event handler when data in the Query has been updated, not how the actual data has been updated.
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                        In order to figure out what changed within the document, we would need to run a new Query and compare the results to that of the previous Query.
                    </list-item>
                  </ordered-list>
 
                <paragraph>
                    To recap, the <code>Changed</code> event is raised each time any document in the Query has a version change.
                    The Changed event itself has access to the original Query data (before any change occurred) via the <code>QueryChangeEventArgs.Rows</code> property, which provides a QueryEnumerator over the original data as follows:
                </paragraph>

                <code-block language="C#"><![CDATA[
                    liveQuery.Changed += (object sender, QueryChangeEventArgs e) => {
                        Debug.WriteLine("Data changed in the query", TAG);
        
                        var rows = e.Rows;

                        rows.ToList().ForEach(row => {
                            var doc = row.Document;
                            // work with Query data ...
                        });
                    };
                ]]>
                </code-block>
            </body>
        </task>


    </tasks>
</lesson>
